你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到pwn学院的漏洞自动发掘模块
welcome back to the Automated Vulnerability Discovery   Module of pwn College
在这个视频中，我们将讨论模糊测试
in this video we're talking about fuzzing
模糊测试是一种动态分析技术
fuzzing is a dynamic analysis technique
从某种意义上说，它是动态分析技术之王
it is the king of dynamic analysis techniques in some        sense
提醒一下，动态分析技术是围绕
and as a reminder dynamic analysis technique is this built around
是围绕这样一个概念构建的
dynamic analysis techniques are built around this concept that
你能运行一个程序
you can run a program
能看到它会做什么
you can see what it does
你可以据此做出推断
and you can make inferences based off of that
模糊测试的起源可追溯到20世纪50年代
fuzzing had its origins way back in the 1950s
我找到了这篇博文
I tracked down this blog post
这是我能找到的，关于模糊测试的最早的参考资料
this is as early as I could find a reference to the concept  of fuzzing
当时，它们测试的程序还写在卡片上
and back then to test their programs which were on punch cards
通过在卡片上打孔来编程
programmed on punch cards
开发人员会用之前丢弃的打孔卡
developers would take previously discarded punch cards  which
读取里面的数据
you know could be read for their data
并使用它们
and use them
把它们作为输入，输入到他们想要测试的程序中
fed them as input into the programs that they were trying  to test
这些都是意外数据
just unexpected data
这就是模糊测试
that is fuzzing
向程序提供意外数据
the feeding of unexpected data to programs
看看他们是否会出现意外行为
to see if they will misbehave
模糊测试是在20世纪80年代形成的
fuzzing was kind of scientifically framed in the 1980s
30年后在一次学术会议上被重新探索和描述
30 years later rediscovered and described at an academic conference
这是一个顶级软件工程会议
one of the top software engineering conferences
最初的想法是
and the original idea
很简单
there was pretty simple
你运行程序
you run the program
给它发送随机的东西
you send it random stuff
看它是否会崩溃
and you see if it crashes
结论是
and the takeaway was
当发送随机输入时，很多东西都表现异常
hey lots of stuff misbehaves when sent random input
事实上，这里我展示了一个非常简单的fuzzer
in fact what I'm showing you here is a very simple fuzzer
它是用bash编写的，带有一点python
it written in bash and with a little python stub
你发送随机数据
you send random data
这里用的cat /dev/urandom
this cat /dev/urandom
这是一个随机数据的接口
this is a random interface
内核的接口
a interface to the kernel
内核会将随机数据发送到这个文件
where the kernel will send you random data on that file
你可以运行任何你想运行的程序
and you run whatever you program you want to run
看看它会不会崩溃
and see if it crash
效果惊人
it's surprisingly effective
我们看一个不同的例子
let's take a look for a different example
实际上不追求崩溃
actually not for crashing
我们有一个compare程序
we have this compare program that takes
发生了什么事?
what is going on
我们有一个compare程序
we have this compare program
它接收一个字母
that takes one letter
失败了会告诉我
and tells me that I failed
用strings查看一下这个程序
if I look at the strings of this program
能看到里面有一个success字符串
I can see that there is a success
所以应该有一个可触发的成功案例
so there should be a triggerable success case
因为它只读一个字母
for because it only reads one letter
剩下的都被送到shell了
the rest get sent to my shell
总之，我们写一个fuzzer来搞定它
anyways let's write a fuzzer to solve this
我们是这样做的
here's what we do
你可以看到
and you can see it's
这些失败正在闪烁
these failures that are blinking
因为每过一会
because every once in a while
会得到正确的输出
you get the correct output
上面写着success
and it said success
实际上我们可以
we can actually
将输出镜像到/dev/stderr
mirror that output to /dev/stderr
然后我们就能看到它
and then we can actually see it
哦,上帝
oh God
好吧
okay
这是一个错误
that was a mistake
我向终端发送了一堆二进制数据
I just sent a bunch of binary data to my terminal
不弄了
we won't do that
但基本上
but basically
我从上个视频中知道
I know from the last video
它需要一个*
that this takes a star
成功了
and that was the success
所以255次中的每一次
so every one out of 255 times
哦，256次中的1次
oh one out of 256 times
我们发送了一个*
we end up sending a star
它是正确的
it's the correct thing
我们触发了成功
and we hit success
你可以很轻松地想象到
and you can easily imagine of course
我们也可以通过这种方式引发崩溃
that we can also trigger crashes this way
这是非常有效的
and this is surprisingly effective
即使是这样的一个简单fuzzer
even these simple fuzzers even now
即使是现在，你在ubuntu上运行它
if you run this on an installable ubuntu
你会发现一些崩溃
you will find crashes
有人在babysuid做系列题目时，来找我
there were people coming to me in the babysuid module
说嘿，我写了这个
saying hey I wrote this
想通过模糊测试来获得flag
just to try to fuzz programs to get the flag
然后我发现了一堆崩溃
and I found a bunch of crashes
是的，它非常有效
yes it's shockingly effective
即使是这样一个简单的想法
even this simple idea
我一直说崩溃
so I keep saying crashes
有一个monitor_for_crash.py
and there was a monitor_for_crashes.py
这是为什么?
why is that
为什么我们的示例fuzzer要找崩溃
why does our example fuzzer conceptually look for           crashes
因为崩溃有吸引力
well it's because crashes are attractive
崩溃是非常令人兴奋的
crashes are very exciting
崩溃意味着内存损坏
crashes imply memory corruption
内存损坏预示着有实现代码执行的可能
memory corruption applies the potential for achieving       code execution
而且崩溃是很容易看到的
but and crashes are very easy to see
它们在程序外很容易看
they're very noticeable from outside of the program
你不用对程序做些复杂的事，来观察是否崩溃
you don't actually need to do crazy stuff to the program to see if it has crashed
调用进程可以简单地调用wait
the calling process can simply call wait
wait将返回终止码
and wait will return the termination code
然后你就知道这个进程是否崩溃了
and then you know that the process has crashed
这非常有用
which is super useful
有些fuzzer
there are fuzzers
可以检测到其他类型的漏洞
that can detect other types of vulnerabilities
在竞争条件模块，我谈到了能识别竞争条件的fuzzer
I talked about fuzzers that can identify race conditions in  the race condition module
有识别攻击算法的fuzzer
there are fuzzers that identify algorithmic attacks
识别信息泄露的Fuzzers
fuzzers that identify information disclosure
但这更难做到
but this is harder to do
要识别竞争条件
to identify race condition
你需要考虑
you need to reason about the
实际状态和互斥锁的正确状态，等等
actual versus the correct state of mutexes etc etc etc
这是一件相当棘手的事情
it's a pretty tricky business
所以人们倾向于关注内存损坏
so people tend to focus on memory corruption
我们得到了内存损坏
so we got the memory corruption
我们讲了这个简单的fuzzer
we have the simple fuzzer
在这之后
after this
在2010年代初
in the early 2010s
人们转向了生成式模糊测试
people have moved on to generational fuzzing
他们意识到
so they realized hey if I actually just
如果我直接发送随机数到图像处理库
send /dev/urandom to an image processing library
它立马会说，嘿，这不是JPEG
it is going to very quickly say hey that's not a JPEG
它不会执行
and it'll won't actually execute
所有我们感兴趣的JPEG库或PNG库代码
all that juicy code deep inside Lib JPEG or Lib PNG
我们想要执行它
that I actually want to get executed
才能观察里面的bug
so that you know I can observe bugs in it
于是人们发明了一种生成式的模糊测试技术
and so people created a technique called generational fuzzing
这个想法很直接
the idea is fairly straightforward
创建一个文件生成器
you create a file generator
例如，如果我对objdump进行模糊测试
for example if I'm fuzzing objdump
它以ELF文件作为输入
which takes ELF files as input
我会创建ELF文件
I will create ELF files
我有一个脚本generate_elf_file.py
and I have a script generate_elf_file.py
它会输出一堆ELF文件
that just shoots out a bunch of ELF files
稍微有点畸形，但可以识别为ELF文件
slightly maybe malformed but recognizable as ELF files
然后我把它们发送到objdump中
and then I send them into objdump
这种fuzzer的一个例子是Peach
an example of this type of fuzzer is Peach fuzzer
Peach是一个文件格式模糊测试器
Peach fuzz is a file format Fuzzer
它接受XML指定的文件格式
that takes a file format specified in XML
并生成它的例子
and generates examples of it
我在我的研究中使用过它
I've used it in my research
如果你需要生成有效的文件，它就很好
it's pretty good stuff if you need to generate valid files
还可以使用其他技巧
and can use other techniques for example
这将带我们来到现代
this brings us to the modern day
要说的是突变模糊测试
which is mutational fuzzing
突变式与生成式不是同一种模糊测试
mutational fuzzing is a different class of fuzzers from       generational fuzzing
突变式的会基于已有输入进行变形
mutational fuzzing mutate existing inputs
来尝试触发新bug和新的代码路径
to try to trigger new bugs and new code
现在看来，这是一种很好的尝试
this is kind of now a very hacky best attempt
基本上有一个循环
but basically you have a loop
在里面，随机选择之前用过的输入
where you pick some random input that you've tried before
你会改变它
and you change it
反转一个比特位
you flip a bit
或旋转它
you rotate it
你把它切分出来
you splice it out
可能和其它输入拼接起来
maybe splice it with other input as well
然后你试一下，看看程序是否会崩溃
and then you try that and see if the program crashes
这里有几个核心问题
so there's a couple of core questions here
一是我们如何选择哪些输入进行改变
one is how do we select what inputs to mutate
二如何改变这些输入
and 2 how do we mutate these inputs
这把我们带到了最近五年的前沿
and this brings us to really the cutting edge or of the last half decade let's say
就是代码路径覆盖引导的突变模糊测试
which is code coverage guided mutational fuzzing
现代的fuzzer有这样的逻辑
modern fuzzers have logic like this
它们从一堆输入开始
they start with a a bunch of inputs
他们会把一堆数据输入程序
a bunch of data that they will feed into the program
这被称为种子语料库
this is called the seed corpus
这些是种子
these are seeds
我们会用这些种子，种出树来
and from these seeds we will grow trees
然后它们进入这个分析循环
and then they enter this analysis loop
它们会在这里用输入执行程序
where they will execute the program with every pending    input
最初用的种子语料库
initially this is the seed corpus
它们会记录下执行的指令
they'll record what instructions were executed
或记录下在处理这些输入时，覆盖到的代码路径
or what coverage happened when processing these          pending inputs
他们会标记出增加了代码覆盖率的输入
they'll mark the inputs that increase the code coverage
执行了新的指令的输入
that executed new instructions
标记为有趣的
as interesting
比如，这是一个有趣的输入
say hey this is an interesting input
它执行了新的指令
that triggered new instruction
也许我们稍微调整一下这个输入
maybe if we tweak it a little bit more
它还会触发新的东西
it'll trigger even new things
或者稍微调整一下
or if we tweak it a little bit more
它会触发一个bug
it'll trigger a bug
然后变异fuzzer
so then the mutational fuzzer
会改变这些输入
will mutate those inputs
最近增加了代码覆盖率的输入
the inputs that have recently increased code coverage
生成一组新的待使用输入
to produce a new set of pending inputs
这样循环下去，直到我们找到bug
and the cycle continues until we find bugs
这里有几件事要注意
so a couple of things here
一，我们如何建立这个种子语料库
1 how do we build this seed corpus
二，我们如何识别代码覆盖率的增加
2 how do we identify increases in code coverage
三，我们如何改变这些输入
and 3 how do we mutate these inputs
这里这句话你应该挺熟悉的
from here this quote should be familiar now
在这个模块的介绍视频中出现过
from the introduction video of this module
从现在开始，我们将讨论
from here we're going to be talking about
AFL
American Fuzzy Lop
AFL的创始人讲的这句话
the creation of the person that made this quote
AFL
American Fuzzy Lop
是覆盖引导突变模糊测试的一种实现
is a specific implementation of coverage guided              mutational fuzzing
它是
it was
我不知道它是不是首个实现的
I don't know if it was the first implementation of it
但它绝对是最声名远播的
but it was definitely the first widely radically famous         implementation of it
它算是永久改变了程序分析的世界
then it kind of changed the world of program analysis       forever
首先我们来谈谈
so first let's talk about
你会传递给AFL的种子语料库
the seed corpus that you would pass to American Fuzzy   Lop to AFL
我懵了一下
my mind just went blank
总之，种子语料库很重要
anyways the seed corpus this is critical
你们可能听说过
so you might have heard
无限猴子理论，说
the infinite monkey theorem says
可以将一群猴子和一堆打字机放在一起
you can put a bunch of monkeys with a bunch of              typewriters
然后让他们随机敲打字机
and have them hit them randomly
最后你能看到莎士比亚的作品
and eventually you will have the works of Shakespeare
但这需要很长很长的时间
but that's gonna take a very very very long time
同样，如果你发送一堆随机数据
in the same way if you send a bunch of random data
然后你对这些随机数进行突变修改
and you start sending doing a bunch of random mutations off that random data
即使使用覆盖引导，你也需要花费很长时间
it's going to take you a very long time even with coverage guided feedback
才能实现一些有用的东西
to achieve something useful right
所以你的种子语料能帮助猴子
so your seed corpus helps the monkeys
你的种子语料库应该多种多样
your seed corpus should be varied
它应该代表
it should represent kind of
能对程序功能有良好的覆盖
a good coverage of program functionality
如果你在模糊测试图像处理库
if you are fuzzing an image processing library
它支持多种文件格式
and it supports multiple files formats
你应该，抱歉
you should excuse me
你的种子语料库中应该有多种图片格式
you should have multiple formats in your seed corpus
如果你正在测试一个ELF处理库
if you are fuzzing a elf processing library
你可以考虑放置许多不同架构的elf
you might consider putting ELFs of lots of different          architectures
诸如此类的事情
and all of these sort of things
它应该稍微有点怪
it should be slightly weird
应该接近程序的边缘情况
it should be close to edge cases of the program
这样fuzzer只修改一点
so that the fuzzer can fuzz it a little bit and
就能触发奇怪的行为
trigger really weird behavior
最简单的方法是什么
what's the easiest way to do this
最简单的方法就是
the easiest way to do this is to look at
看看相关代码中触发bug的poc输入
proof of concept inputs that have triggered bugs in related code
把它当作种子
and use that as seeds
所以如果你在模糊测试图像处理库
so there if you're fuzzing an image processing library
并且你听过另一个图像处理库中的一个bug
and you heard about a different bug in a different image   processing library
就去看看那个库中触发bug的输入图像
go look at the image that triggers that bug in that library
把它放到你要测试的库里
and put it in the library you're fuzzing
理论上，它很可能接近触发bug的输入
and the likeliest scenarios it's conceptually closer to an     input that will trigger bugs
由于一些未知原因，bug往往聚集在一起
bugs tend to cluster for a weird reason that people don't  necessarily understand
你的语料库，或库中的种子
and your corpus or the individual seeds of your corpus
不一定是语料库本身
not the corpus itself necessarily
但单独的种子应该尽量小
but the individual seeds should be fairly small
AFL
AFL as it functions
会尝试修改你的输入的每一个比特位
will eventually try to mutate every bit of your inputs
不要放没用的比特位
don't put useless bits
每一个无用的比特，都会减少AFL探索新代码的时间
every useless bit reduces the amount of time that AFL is   exploring new code
所以如果你在模糊测试C编译器
so if you're fuzzing the C compiler
你不会想把注释放到语料库中
you probably don't want comments in your seed corpus for example
这可能不是一个好例子
that might be a bad example but
但这是一个例子
it is an example
你还需要种子语料库尽量小
and also you want a small seed corpus in the sense that
因为，你想用最少的种子
you want the smallest number of seeds
覆盖所有
that can still cover all of the functionality
你能触发的功能
that you are able to trigger
物尽其用
using all the seeds that you are disposed on the program
而不是屯一堆放在那里
rather than having a bunch of
这是大小和覆盖范围之间的平衡
this is a balance between size and coverage
不要持有一堆小种子，每个触发一个功能
rather than having a bunch of tiny seeds that each trigger one functionality
有时，只用少量的种子，触发大量功能，是有益的
it can sometimes be beneficial to have few seeds that       trigger a lot of functionality
这样就可以执行一次程序，获得大量代码交互
so that you can get a lot of interaction within a single run of the binary going
这显然是一种平衡
this is obviously a balance
你不想要的是
which you really don't want are
由很多无效字节的大的输入
large inputs  that have a lot of this sort of deadwait bytes that
因为在它们身上发生的突变，是没有意义的
for which mutation is pointless
比如注释
like comments
接着我们讲讲代码覆盖率的测量
then we're moving on to measuring code coverage
那么你怎么测量
so how do you measure
你是否触发了新的代码路径
if you have triggered extra coverage
实际上有很多技术可以做到这一点
there's actually a wide number of techniques that exist for this
以及方法
and philosophies and so forth
例如，你可以跟踪记录执行的每条指令
you might track for example every instruction that was     executed
跟踪记录执行的基础代码块
you might track every basic block that was executed
把它作为覆盖范围
and use that as coverage
而AFL的做法是
what American Fuzzy lop does
它看重的，不是输入触发的代码
is relying the input that it's not necessarily the code you    trigger that matters
而是它如何遍历代码
is how you traverse that code
在相同的函数中
you might have the same function
如果你按特定顺序执行代码块
and if you go through basic blocks in a given order
它可能有不同的功能
it might have a different functionality
相比于按另一个顺序执行相同的代码块
than if you go through the same basic blocks in a different order
所以AFL测量控制流转换
so AFL measures control flow transitions
将基础代码块和jmp指令配对
pairs of basic blocks connected by jumps
这就是它衡量代码覆盖率的方法
and that's how it measures code coverage
终于说到如何改变代码了
and then finally how do you mutate code
AFL有几种不同的改变方式
AFL mutates using several different mutators
一是遍历输入数据，每次反转 L比特位
one mutator goes through and flips L bits at a time
遍历时的步长为 S比特位
and walks the input file with S bit increments
这是第一种改变方式
that's one that's its first mutator
第二种方式，以8位为步长，遍历输入，每次加或减一个值
second mutator it actually does numerical computation     again on increments of the file
第三种方式，用感兴趣的值，替换部分输入
then it swaps parts of the file with interesting values
感兴趣的值，指在边界的值
so values that are you know right on the edge of a bit      boundary
这可能会触发off-by-one错误
that might trigger off by 1 errors
经常触发off-by-one错误
so frequently trigger off by 1 errors
诸如此类的错误
these sort of things
第四种，它还可以注入用户提供的值
it can inject user supply dictionary terms
如果你在模糊测试一个XML文件
if you're fuzzing an XML file
那用一些XML实体拿去模糊测试，还是很有用的
then it's useful to put a dictionary with some XML entities and so forth
那在这一步，AFL就会将输入变异成你给的值
that in this step AFL will actually mutate into your inputs
AFL会做各种随机的调整
it will do various random tweaks
还有一个很有趣的
and then a very interesting one
它会将多个输入拼接在一起
it will splice multiple inputs together
这些
so these mutated mutation mutators sorry
这些突变方法
these mutators basically
加上那个循环
in the combination with that loop
以及给定输入触发了多少代码的指标
with the fitness metric of how much code given input has  triggered
这就把突变模糊变成了一种遗传算法
this turns mutational fuzzing into a genetic algorithm
如果你学过包含遗传算法的算法课程
if you have taken an algorithmic course that covers          genetic algorithms
遗传算法会分析一个解决方案
genetic algorithms analyze a solution
确定其适应度函数
determine its fitness function
然后改变它
and then mutate it
并将其与其他合适的解决方案结合起来
and breed it with other fit solutions
AFL对输入也做同样的事情
AFL does the same thing with inputs
我多次提到模糊测试方法是王者
I mentioned several times fuzzing is king
而AFL是王者之中的王者
and that AFL specifically is king
模糊测试无疑是我们所拥有的最好的程序分析技术
fuzzing is undeniably the best program analysis technique that we have
它每年都会发现数千个bug
it finds thousands of bugs every year
你可以在这张图上看到它的影响
and you can see the impact just on this graph
这一年
the year
AFL最初于2013年11月发行
so AFL was released initially in November of 2013
马上
right away
第二年发现的bug数就有大幅增加
there was a massive jump in the bugs that were               discovered the next year
而且这一直持续了下去
and then this has kept going
随着自动化bug查找的研究进入实用阶段
as research in automated bug finding reached practical     stage
我想给你们看一下AFL的README
I want to show you AFL's readme actually
这是这个项目的主页
this is the homepage of the project
这是AFL的照片
this is actually a picture of AFL
在问答直播中，我将介绍如何使用它
in the live Q&A I'll go through how to use it
然后用不同方式使用它
and poke around it in different ways
这里讲了些卖点
there's a sales pitch
然后是这个
and then there's this
每个链接都是AFL发现的bug
each of these links is a bug found by AFL
我很确定他们放弃了追踪记录
at some point I am pretty sure they just gave up keeping   track
这就是AFL
that's just AFL
然后还有fuzzer
then there have been fuzzers
无数fuzzer受AFL启发
countless fuzzers inspired by AFL
并推动超越AFL
and pushing forward past AFL
有太多fuzzer了，难以完整记录
there are too many fuzzers to keep track of
这是一个非常活跃的研究领域
this is a radically active area of research
包括我和我在ASU的同事们的研究实验室
including my research lab along with my colleagues at     Arizona State University
我们正在推动模糊测试向前发展
we are pushing the kind of state of fuzzing forward
以及其他程序分析技术
along with other program analysis techniques
如果你对学术研究感兴趣的话
again if you're interested in doing academic research
不管是不是在ASU
whether or not it's at ASU
给我说句话
shoot me a line
我很乐意回答你们的问题
and I'm happy to answer questions
尤其是如果你能在pwn学院走到这一步
especially if you made it this far in pwn College
回到前沿fuzzer
so cutting edge fuzzers
有太多了，根本记不全
there just too many to keep track of
我会指出一些很酷的资源
I'll instead point out some really cool resources
有一个叫OSS-Fuzz的项目
there's a project called OSS Fuzz
谷歌和OSS Fuzz的贡献者
basically Google and contributors to OSS Fuzz
利用了大量的开源软件和
have harness a lot of open source software and
将其配置为易于运行和易于模糊测试
configured it to be runnable easily and fuzzable easily
并可分析
and analyzable
然后谷歌持续对这些项目进行模糊测试
and then Google actually goes through a continuously       fuzzes these projects
然后报告bug
and then of course reports the bugs
很难准确说出发现了多少bug
and it's hard to even say how many bugs were found
但这是
but it is
是一个数不清的数字
it is countless numbers
谷歌还有一个很酷的项目叫syzkaller
there is a really cool project also from Google called        syzkaller
它是Linux系统的fuzzer
it is a system call fuzzer for Linux
它在用户空间fuzzlinux内核
so it fuzzes from user space up into the Linux kernel
查找内核bug
to find kernel bugs
我个人在我的研究中使用过它
I've used it personally in my research
非常棒
it's quite awesome
还有另一大家族的fuzzer
there is another kind of family of fuzzers
基于LLVM编译器的另一个分支
or another lineage based on LLVM the compiler                infrastructure
现在主要由苹果和贡献者开发
now mostly developed by apple and contributors
libfuzzer
需要源代码
requires source code
这是一个集成的模糊测试库
it's a integrated fuzzing library
它集成到clang和LLVM
that's integrating to clang and LLVM
实际上OSS Fuzz也使用了libfuzzer
and actually OSS Fuzz uses libfuzzer as well
这是在软件开发过程中模糊测试的好方法
and it's a great way to fuzz your software during              development
然后是
and then there is
并将它集成到你的测试用例中
and to integrate into your test cases for your applications
然后是AFL++
and then there's AFL plus plus
AFL的最初开发者
the original developer of AFL
在更新之间，花了些时间
takes time between updates
于是社区创建了AFL++
and so the community created AFL plus plus
加入了一些社区支持的修改
with some community supported editions
还有一个很好的清单
there's also this great list
实际上有几个列表
actually there's several lists
这是其中之一
but here's one of them
你可以在这里找到大量的资源、书籍和论文链接
where you can get tons of fuzzing resources, books, links  to papers
有很多很酷的东西
a lot of really cool stuff
如果你对这类东西感兴趣
again if this sort of stuff interests you
给我写封邮件，我们来谈谈
drop me a line and we'll talk about research
下个视频见
see you in the next video